Much to my surprise, a particular
saturated fat may not be the bad guy in
this story of cancer, while another
takes the hot seat. Recently,
researchers aim to identify if different
fats affect cancer progression. The
answer is yes, by the way. But
additionally, they found that certain
fats can paralyze our immune system into
not combating cancer. So, what in the
world is going on? And where in the
world is Carmen San Diego? I'll give you
the answer to the first question because
I have no idea on the second. The reason
I was surprised is because one fat
source is high in a reliably damaging
saturated fat called palmitic acid and
the other is lower in palmitic acid but
contains more steic acid. The surprising
part is that the fat source with more
palmitic acid is not the one of concern
here. Rather, the one with more steic
acid is. In fact, I mentioned these fats
paralyze our immune system, which is
vital for fighting off cancer. And it
just so happens that this steic acid is
especially paralyzing. We can see that
here as we look at immune cell killing
ability. Essentially, the researchers
put immune cells and cancer cells
together at increasing concentrations of
immune cells and then measure the amount
of cancer cell death. The higher up the
lines are, the more cancer cells
survive. We have three conditions here.
The black line is the condition where
nothing is added to the cells. The blue
is the molecule used to compare against.
And the final condition in yellow is
when steic acid is added to the cells.
Clearly, when steic acid is exposed to
the immune cells, they lose their
ability to kill cancer cells. Now,
admittedly, it would have been good to
have an additional condition here
because we can't tease out based on the
data that we just went over if steic
acid is the cause or the exposure to any
fat. To be fair, the researchers look at
other outcomes looking at different fats
and show a unique effect of steic acid.
But for this specific experiment, they
missed an opportunity, I think. At any
rate, taking all this data together,
we're looking at steeric acid, not
palmitic acid, as the prime culprit for
freezing or paralyzing, to use our word
earlier, from destroying cancer cells.
But there's more to this. For example,
when looking at sources of steic acid,
butter stands out to the researchers.
And when compared against another
saturated fat source like palm oil, the
results are striking in how they affect
the immune system. When measuring the
fat inside the immune cells, the actual
fat droplets like the cell is
overburdened with fat, it was the butter
condition that led to immune cells being
overburdened with fat, not the palm oil
or the control condition. This in
conjunction with additional data
implicated butter as a source of immune
paralysis, thereby allowing cancer free
reign for growth. And this could at
least partly be mediated by steic acid
found in butter. And when looking at
actual tumors in mice, we have the
butterheavy food compared against
standard food without butter or palm
oil. Body weight is on the left side for
both. And the line is the progression of
the tumor size over time. Clearly in the
butter condition, there is an
acceleration of tumor size. And
surprisingly, although the body weight
was also increased, the palm oil did not
lead to an acceleration of tumor size.
Although calories and nutrient
composition was the same, this would
directly implicate butter as a cancer
accelerant. But there's a lot to
contextualize here, which we'll dive
into. But if you're looking for a deeper
understanding like exactly why the
immune cells become paralyzed or if
other common sources of fat also have
these effects, including things like
olive oil, then check out the insider
version of this video that you're
watching. It also comes with a helpful
article. And let's not forget the many
perks like a private podcast, live
sessions with me and more. And of
course, weekly articles and videos, and
well, the community. Check it out using
the link in the description. Now, to
contextualize this, well, for one, we
know that an obesogenic environment
affects our immune cells as other
studies have indicated that to be the
case. So, that likely is one contributor
to accelerated cancer progression.
However, it doesn't explain the
differences between sources of fat. We
saw some evidence that saturated fat
steeric acid is especially harmful when
combating cancer. But as I briefly
pointed out and I'll say now, some of
these data are incomplete, especially
considering palm oil also contains steic
acid and does not yield these same
negative effects. One explanation
offered is that the steic acid from the
food needs to be converted into a
similar but slightly different molecule
called steroid carnitine. And it's
actually this molecule that yields these
negative effects. And the researchers of
the study mentioned that because there
was more steic acid consumed with butter
that explains the elevation in steroid
carnitine. The other consideration and
the most obvious one is a reliance on
animal data. But since it's extremely
difficult to do randomized control
trials on cancer in humans and
especially when there's something that
may harm them, we have to rely on
longerterm associative data. It just so
happens that across the social media
world, a big study looking at butter and
cancer got a lot of public publicity.
Now, in that study, the researchers
found an association between a greater
butter consumption and increased cancer
mortality. I'd like to see more data,
but as it stands, the evidence is
leaning against butter and cancer. I
think it should also be noted that the
main study that we've been going over is
primarily looking at melanoma. I don't
see why this wouldn't translate to other
types of cancer, but we don't actually
know that for a fact. And as a final
quick point, none of these diets were a
ketogenic diet. So we're talking about a
well-controlled scenario in this main
study with all things kept equal as
possible. But this doesn't directly
inform on ketogenic states. We need
separate experimentation for that. So
what are the main points here? So for
one, we saw direct evidence that when
cancer is already present, the saturated
fat-filled butter accelerates tumor
growth and the saturated fat-filled palm
oil does not. That may be due to
differences in steic acid content.
Secondly, while more data is needed,
these data indicate that reducing your
butter consumption if you have cancer,
especially melanoma, could be a simple
and easy step to reducing the risk of
cancer progression. And third, there is
a fat, not mentioned here, that actually
fights cancer, but is mentioned right
here in this next video. I hope this was
informative, and I'll catch you soon.
Thanks for watching.